原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/sknX7VxXQG8
原视频发布日期：20201126
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
On monday night China's Lunar exploration program took a huge step forward with the launch of Chang'e 5.
周一晚上 随着嫦娥五号的发射 中国的月球探测计划向前迈出了一大步
This spacecraft is aiming to go to the moon land on the surface
这艘航天器的目标是前往月球并着陆月球表面
and return a sample of the moon to the earth.
并将月球样本送回地球
And this has not been performed since 1976 with the Luna 24 mission.
而这是自1976年的月球24号任务以来 从未进行过的
So this is a monster spacecraft which is much more capable than those 1970s Soviet spacecraft.
所以这是一个怪兽级的航天器 比70年代的苏联航天器功能更强大
It's 8.2 tons.
它重达8.2吨
It's multiple stages, multiple parts.
它是多级 多部件的
To get this onto a trans-lunar trajectory,
为了让它进入月球转移轨道
they needed to use the largest rocket that China has, the Long March 5.
他们需要使用中国最大的火箭 长征五号
And this is a big step up technologically for China.
这是中国在技术上的一大进步
Previously they've been working with these, you know,
此前他们一直在使用这些 你知道的
hypergolic fuel boosters are derived ultimately from ICBMs.
技术最初来源于洲际弹道导弹的自燃燃料助推器
But Long March 5 is modern.
但长征五号是现代化的
It's a cryogenic rocket has better performance.
这是一枚有更好性能的低温燃料火箭
It's launched next to the sea from an island.
它是从海边的一个岛屿上进行的发射
So that it drops its stages in in the water rather than on land.
所以它的分级会落在水里而不是陆地上
So yeah it has four boosters around the outside which are high performance kerosene liquid oxygen boosters.
是的 它(一级)外面有四个高性能的煤油液氧助推器
The core is liquid hydrogen and there's two stages on that.
芯级有两个分级 其使用的是液氢(和液氧)推进剂
And that was able to launch the spacecraft towards the moon.
这样就能把航天器发射到月球上
So it's going to take a few days to get there.
那么需要几天的时间才能到达那里
It's currently about 300 000 kilometers from the earth approaching the moon right now.
目前它距离地球约30万公里 正在接近月球
When it gets to the moon, it's going to perform multiple breaking burns
当它到达月球时 它将进行多次减速点火
so it's going to take several burns to actually break itself into Lunar orbit into a 200 kilometer orbit.
那么它要经过几次点火才能真正进入到高度200km的绕月轨道上
And then when it's ready to land
当它准备降落时
it will slow itself down even more, putting its perilune about 15 kilometers above the surface.
它将进一步减慢自己的速度 把近月点降低到15km
It will then detach the lander
然后分离着陆器
and the lander will perform an autonomous landing at the site.
而着陆器将在指定的着陆点进行自主着陆
So the lander is actually not dumb.
那么着陆器其实并不笨
It's full of scientific instruments.
它充满了科学仪器
It's going to have visual and infrared spectrometers to analyze the materials there.
其中包括用于分析着陆点位置附近材料的可见光和红外光谱仪
It's going to have ground penetrating radar.
以及探地雷达
So they're going to be able to pick and choose what samples they want to return.
所以这样就可以选择想要返回的样品
They have a drill which is able to drill two meters down.
还有一个能够钻到两米深的钻头
So that's comparable to the drilling capabilities of previous sampling missions
那么这与之前的采样任务的钻探能力相当
and then all of this will be loaded into a return vehicle.
然后所有这些东西都会被装进返回器(上升器)里
So the return vehicle sits on top of the lander and it's about 120 kilograms.
那么上升器位于着陆器的顶部 大约有120kg重
So I believe it gets pushed off by springs initially
那么我相信它一开始是用弹簧推开的(而不是其他带有破坏性的火工品)
because they want to preserve the lander for as long as possible.
因为他们想让着陆器尽可能地(不要受到破坏而)保存得更久
And yeah 120 kilograms pushes the hardware into orbit.
是的没错 120kg的上升器 足以入轨
That's about 250 pounds by the way if you're speaking imperial.
英制的话大约是250lb
I think this makes it the smallest rocket able to reach orbit from the surface of a planetary body.
我认为这将使它成为能够从行星体表面入轨的最小火箭
And I say planetary as in something that's been spherical.
我说的行星体是指球形的物体
From there it doesn't go all the way back to earth on its own.
从那儿开始 上升器并不会一路独自返回地球
The orbiter which has been hanging out there the whole time.
一直绕月飞行的轨道器
It will creep up and rendezvous with the spacecraft
会慢慢地与上升器交会
dock and then transfer the samples into a return capsule or re-entry vehicle.
再对接 然后将样品转移到返回舱或再入航天器(返回器)中
After that they'll detach the docking adapter
之后 他们会分离对接适配器
and the orbiter with the return capsule will remain in orbit until the planets align
而携带返回器的轨道器将一直在轨道上运行 直到(轨道)对准行星(地球)
and it begins its journey home probably in the first couple of weeks of December.
之后 可能在12月的前几周 它将开始回家的旅程
It'll take a few days to fall down through the gravity well.
它需要几天时间在重力井中坠下
Until it arrives at Earth, it will detach the re-entry capsule.
在它到达地球时 它将分离返回器
The re-entry capsule is very similar in design to the Shenzhou or Soyuz-style capsules.
返回器的设计与神舟或联盟式的返回舱非常相似
It will use a skip re-entry which means it will use aerodynamic forces.
它将使用跳跃式再入 这意味着它将使用空气动力
Once it hits the atmosphere, it will curve its trajectory upwards
一旦进入大气层 它就会将轨道向上弯曲
so it has a period of intense heating and breaking.
所以它会经历一段强烈的加热和减速
And then a second it'll skip up and then fall back for a second period of heating.
然后啪的一下 很快啊 它就会打水漂式地跳起来 然后落回 进行第二段加热
And this is apparently easier on the heat shield
而这显然能降低对隔热板的要求
so ultimately it will end up landing under parachute in Inner Mongolia
那么最终其会以降落伞的形式 降落在内蒙古
where there will be teams on hand ready to recover the samples
在那里 会有人员现场准备回收样品
and put them into stable secure facilities
并将其放入稳定安全的设施中
to make sure they are not contaminated by anything from the planet Earth.
以确保它们不被地球上的任何东西污染
So yeah this is a quite a complicated vehicle.
那么是的 这是一个相当复杂的航天器
It's going to be the first automated rendezvous in Lunar orbit.
这将是在月球轨道上的第一次自主交会
Obviously every time Apollo did it, there were people at the controls.
很明显 每次阿波罗号的交会对接都是有人在控制的
When Luna 24 went to the moon, it was a much simpler design.
而当月球24号登上月球时 它的设计要简单得多
It was only able to return if it landed in a specific place.
它只有在特定的地方降落才能返回
They had to pick the landing spot on the moon so that when Luna took off vertically
他们必须选择特定的月球上的着陆点 这样当月球号从月表垂直起飞时
类似的返回可见b23.tv/av96049581
it would like just be able to go in a straight line and end up on a return trajectory for Earth.
就像是沿着一条直线前进 但最后能变成一条返回地球的轨道
With being able to rendezvous in Lunar orbit and then pick the return time,
而能够在月球轨道上交会 并选择返回的时间
they are able to pick their landing site
这样就能选择他们的着陆地点
and this means that apparently when Chang'e 5 if it's a success
而很显然 这也就意味着 如果嫦娥五号成功了
there is a backup spacecraft called Chang'e 6 predictably
嫦娥五号的备份 大概叫嫦娥六号
and with that if it works they will send it to the Lunar south pole and get polar samples as well,
就会前往月球南极 同时也会获得极区的样品
hoping to find more evidence for water.
希望能找到更多的水的证据
Having said that of course the Soviet spacecraft Luna 24 in 1976,
既然说到这里 顺便说下1976年苏联的月球24号航天器
it returned 170 grams of material and some of this when analyzed apparently showed evidence for water
它带回了170克材料 其中一些材料在分析后明显显示出水的证据
but many people at the time dismissed this evidence
但当时很多人对这个证据不屑一顾
because they thought it was the result of ground contamination
因为他们认为这是地面污染造成的
because they thought that the moon was far too dry and could not possibly have any water in it.
因为他们认为月球太干燥了 不可能有水的存在
Okay so the landing site is interesting.
好吧 那么 着陆地点很有趣
It's a place called Mons Rümker.
这是一个叫吕姆克山的地方
What they wanted to do was get some of the youngest material on the moon.
他们想在月球上采集一些最新的物质
So like the Apollo missions, they went to places like the Sea of Tranquility, the Ocean of Storms.
就像阿波罗任务一样 他们去了静海和风暴洋这样的地方
Well Mons Rümker is in the middle of the Oceans of Storms also known as Oceanus Procellarum
吕姆克山就在风暴洋的中间 也就是所谓的Oceanus Procellarum
雨海
风暴洋
南极-艾特肯盆地
and it's basically a volcano.
它基本上是一座火山
And according to spacecraft that have surveyed the moon and looked at it through spectrometers,
根据航天器对月球的勘测 比如通过光谱仪来观察它
it's believed that this is a lava flow or a mount lava volcano that has high levels of radiological materials.
据信这是熔岩流或熔岩火山 有着较高水平的放射性物质
候选着陆点
嫦娥五号着陆区域
吕姆克
德兴陨石坑
夏普陨石坑A
瑙曼陨石坑B
Things like Uranium and Thorium, Potassium. Things that could have kept the moon warm.
比如铀 钍 钾这些可以让月球保持温暖的物质
So it's believed that this came up through the Ocean of storms
那么这些物质应该是从风暴洋(的下方)涌上来的
and formed a volcano possibly as recently as a billion years ago
并可能在10亿年这么近的时间之前 形成了一座的火山
and it may have been driven by radiogenic heating from these materials.
而这可能是由这些材料的辐射热驱动的
Now the Apollo spacecraft, they were looking for nice easy places to land.
那么阿波罗航天器 他们会考虑着陆点是否容易进行着陆
This is an automated spacecraft.
而嫦娥五号是一个(无人)自主的航天器
They are quite confident in their navigation capabilities
而设计人员对他们研制出的导航能力很有信心
so it looks like they are going to try and land on something like this if they can.
那么看起来如果可以的话 他们会尝试在这样(困难)的东西上降落
The spacecraft itself is fully autonomous.
航天器本身是完全自主的
It's going to use Lidar, Radar.
它将使用激光测距仪和雷达
It's going to use image processing to feature identification
以及图像处理能力来进行特征识别
to try and pick out a landing site and put itself down on the surface.
试图选择一个着陆点 并把自己降落在月表上
Now they're going to have a limited amount of time to perform this sampling operation.
那么 他们要在有限的时间内进行这次取样操作
The spacecraft is entirely solar powered and isn't expected to last the Lunar night.
航天器完全由太阳能驱动 而且预计不能熬过月夜
So the sun rises over the site I believe tomorrow.
所以我相信明天太阳就会从这里升起
If you look by the way at the moon tomorrow night,
如果你顺便看看明晚的月亮
the Ocean of Storms if you're in the northern hemisphere is the dark area on the left side of the moon
如果你在北半球的话 风暴洋 就是月亮左边的黑暗区域
as viewed from the northern hemisphere if you're in the south it's on the other side.
如果你在南半球 那就在另一边
And Mons Rümker is going to be in there so that's where they're waiting for.
而他们等待着陆的吕姆克山就在那儿
Therefore they can't land there until daylight comes
因此 在天亮之前 他们不能在那里着陆
and then they have two weeks of daylight to make sure that
然后 他们有两个星期的日光 以确保
they can perform their sampling, power their instruments, drill down, get that and then return it to space.
他们可以进行取样 给仪器供电 钻下去 得到这些样品 然后再送回太空
It's possible this spacecraft, this probe, this lander continues to work after Lunar night but I wouldn't count on it.
这个航天器 探测器 着陆器 有可能在月夜之后继续工作 但不能这样指望它完成任务
Also by the way in terms of reusing hardware, I've heard that it's entirely possible that
另外顺便说一下 我听说 在设备的重复使用方面 完全有可能是
they might be considering to reuse the propulsion vehicle, the service module.
他们可能会考虑重新使用推进器 即服务舱(轨道器)
应该是指嫦娥五号T1飞行试验器的服务舱
This has happened in the past where they did a test with a service module
过去曾发生过这种情况 他们用服务舱做了一次测试
and then they swung it back out to the moon.
然后把它甩回月球
It flew past the the earth back out towards the moon.
它飞过了地球 回到了月球
I'm not sure what they would do with it but if it's hardware in space
我不知道他们会用它来做什么 但如果它是太空中的设备的话
they might you might figure out how to preserve it.
你可能会想办法来保存它
I mean there's been a lot of stuff in the Chang'e spacecraft where they've tried to do new things with it
我是指 他们试图用嫦娥航天器上的很多设备来做新的研究
And Chang'e 1 was of course just a simple Lunar orbiter and they built Chang'e 2 as a backup.
而当然 嫦娥一号只是一个简单的月球轨道器 同时 他们建造了嫦娥二号作为备份
But after Chang'e 2 went to the moon, it performed a number of orbits
但是嫦娥二号去了月球之后 它绕月工作了一段时间
and then decided to leave the moon headed out to a Lagrange point
然后决定离开月球 前往日地拉格朗日L2点
and for one of the first spacecraft to visit a Lagrange point.
并成为首批访问拉格朗日点的航天器之一
And then they used some good old gravity assists to fly out
然后他们使用一些经典的引力弹弓方法 飞了出去
and intercept the asteroid Toutatis and get some close-up views of that.
之后飞掠了小行星图塔蒂斯 并近距离拍到一些照片
Now Chang'e 3 and 4 were obviously Lunar rovers
那么嫦娥三号和四号显然是(带着)月球车(着陆了)
with Chang'e 4 being the first to land on the far side of the moon.
其中 嫦娥四号是第一个着陆到月球远端的
But yeah Chang'e 5 is the lander, the sampler.
但是啊 嫦娥五号是着陆器 采样器
Hoping this will work.
希望这能成功
This is very cool.
这是非常酷的
If it doesn't, Chang'e 6 is already pretty much built as far as I understand.
如果不行的话 据我了解 嫦娥六号已经造得差不多了
And they will have a future opportunity to fly that.
而且他们将来会有机会发射嫦娥六号的
If Chang'e 5 is successful, they will be able to pick another landing site which would be pretty darn cool as well.
如果嫦娥五号成功 他们就可以选择另一个着陆点 这也是非常酷的
Another interesting thing by the way is that
对了 还有一个有趣的事情是
this spacecraft on the way to the moon has obviously been transmitting and talking to ground control.
这艘航天器在飞往月球的途中 显然一直在与地面控制中心进行数据传输
European Space Agency has also been helping coordinate with China to make sure that they can track this.
欧空局也一直在和中国合作 帮助他们进行追踪
But amateur radio observers have been doing their own thing.
但业余无线电观察员一直也在做他们自己的事情
And of course they've done their usual stuff of getting doppler information, tracking information
当然 惯例 他们做了该做的 比如获取多普勒信息 跟踪信息
and they have been able to receive telemetry signals and decode TV data.
而他们已经能够接收到遥测信号并解码电视数据
And the TV data was apparently in a standard format
而电视数据显然是标准格式的
so we've got this sort of totally uncurated engineering data camera
所以 我们已经得到了这种完全不剪辑的工程相机的数据
showing the solar panels and dust which is pretty amazing.
显示了太阳能电池板和灰尘 而这是非常惊人的
应该是北京时间12月17日00:37:57左右，时间来自 @China航天 weibo.com/5616492130/JvIXD6WoR
But yeah, it's expected that the spacecraft will be returning the capsule to the earth in December 17th.
但是 没错 预计航天器将在12月17日将返回舱送回地球
Round about the same time by the way, Japan will be returning their sample capsule from Ryugu
差不多同一时间 日本将从龙宫返回他们的样品舱
so we're getting a whole bunch of Andromeda Strain potentialities coming.
所以 我们得到了一大堆可能会造成人间大浩劫 的物质
Just kidding.
开个玩笑
Now seriously, December is going to be the month
那么认真地说 在12月
where we return you're two different samples from alien worlds back to the earth.
会发生两次外星样品返回地球的事情
It's going to be complicated.
(嫦娥五号)将是复杂的
It's going to be tricky.
这将是困难的
Luna 23 can tell you just how hard landing on the moon can be.
月球23号任务会告诉你 着陆月球有多难
Hopefully Chang'e 5 doesn't go through that.
希望嫦娥五号不会经历这种情况
And hopefully we get a sample back on the earth just in time for Christmas.
希望我们能在圣诞节前将样本送回地球
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]